<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thomas Davis - Front end web developer</title>
    <description>Thomas Davis is a front end web developer from Brisbane, Australia.   Works heavily in Javascript and CSS/HTML.
</description>
    <link>http://thomasdav.is/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://thomasdav.is/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2014 21:58:55 +1000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2014 21:58:55 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Frontend Frameworks - Which will stand the test of time?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We have seen an exponential increase in the number of startups over the last few years, with an app for everything. I was going to make a joke about even having “Uber for dog walking” but it actually &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2013/04/26/swifto-raises-2-5m-from-benchmark-to-be-the-uber-for-dog-walkin/&quot;&gt;exists&lt;/a&gt; so I guess the joke is on me. One of the best ways to make yourself stand out from the other 43 alternatives to your product is to really nail the user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of your views about Javascript, it has made apps such as Facebook and Google Docs a pleasure to use. This post assumes Javascript apps are here to stay for quite a while longer, I will write another post about what it will take for a new paradigm to usurp the UI throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you accept the fact that they are here to stay, then which framework should you choose for your next application? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Please don&amp;#39;t nitpick what I called a framework here&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;frameworks&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;angular&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;backbone&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;polymer&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;react&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;flight&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;spine&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;ember&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;knockout&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;agility&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;canjs&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;maria&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;extjs&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;sammyjs&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;stapesjs&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;kendo&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to posit a more important question, especially to those whose careers revolve around using any of these frameworks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;which-will-stand-the-test-of-time&quot;&gt;Which will stand the test of time?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these frameworks differ dramatically in their principles. What I mean by principles is that there is most likely only one-ish way that it will make sense to do things going into the future e.g. someone figured out at some stage that web servers shouldn’t block when waiting for I/O.  I personally do not know which ones are heading in the right direction but I do know only a few of these frameworks will influence the real future of UI’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there is a lot of overlap and we can expect development to converge on some best practises. Though if you are in the Angular camp, you would think that HTML is to be extended and agree with their statement;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Other frameworks deal with HTML’s shortcomings by either abstracting away HTML, CSS, and/or JavaScript or by providing an imperative way for manipulating the DOM. Neither of these address the root problem that HTML was not designed for dynamic views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this situation, if you spent the next few years learning one way or the other and it turns out that you are wrong, your career prospects will be diminished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking to hear well thought out opinions on the matter, what will frameworks really look like in the next 5-10 years?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://thomasdav.is/frontend-frameworks-which-will-stand-the-test-of-time</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://thomasdav.is/frontend-frameworks-which-will-stand-the-test-of-time</guid>
        
        
        <category>frontend</category>
        
        <category>frameworks</category>
        
        <category>backbone</category>
        
        <category>angular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The problem with distributed social networks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently the news on the internet has been that the government admits you don’t own your &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/10/governments-attack-cloud-computing&quot;&gt;cloud data&lt;/a&gt;.   Besides this scary totalitarian notion it seems absurd that a company such as Facebook will forever run the social lives of the entire world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily many people have already realized this and have started working on decentralized approaches, you can find a full list on &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distributed_social_network&quot;&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of a distributed social network taken from wikipedia is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A distributed social network is an Internet social network service that is decentralized and distributed across different providers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem-is-distributing-a-distributed-social-network&quot;&gt;The problem is distributing a distributed social network&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently there was a HackerNews &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4418904&quot;&gt;submission&lt;/a&gt; talking about &lt;a href=&quot;tent.io&quot;&gt;tent.io&lt;/a&gt;(one of the listed DSNs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the highest rated comments stated&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Decentralizing things like this is never ever going to work. In terms of running it… my mom/sister/dad/cousin are not going to host this themselves. They might depend on me to do it, but even I’m not going to run a decentralized social network myself. There’s too much liability involved. Not to mention, it’s a pain in the ass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which was refuted by a few comments &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You say decentralized services never work, and then give an example of the most successful one: email.   I don’t know why you are assuming that everyone will have to run their own. Also, it seems very cynical/naive to think that just because such systems aren’t currently working/won’t currently work with given social structures, that this will always be the case. Do you disagree?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Not only is email a successful decentralised system, it’s the logical infrastructure for a decentralised social network. In Facebook terms, your “feed” is just an inbox with a smart filter and nice presentation, and your “wall” is just a mailing list to which all of your friends are subscribed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;current-distribution-techniques&quot;&gt;Current distribution techniques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tent.io/about&quot;&gt;Tent.io&lt;/a&gt; is my favorite approach so far. Starting with a rock solid protocol they have started building server implementations using Ruby. But the first few comments of their about page alude to the problem of distribution to non tech saavy users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tent allows every user to run their own server, but like email and the web, most users will use a hosting service to handle it.
  Users who want to run their own server should look at tentd, the current reference server implementation.
  Alternatively, Tent.is offers one-click Tent hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is ideally all that should be required, but understandably does not seem like the impetus that such a bold movement needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-browser-extensions-for-distribution&quot;&gt;Using browser extensions for distribution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The browser has shown to become a powerful player in app distribution with the Chrome webstore, Firefox Addons and the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what if we could package DSNs servers in browser extensions themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users could then &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easily one click install, cross platform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automatically sync their extensions across computers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find DSNs through exploring app stores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once installed, they could manage their own back ups or use services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-could-you-run-an-entire-server-in-a-browser-extension&quot;&gt;How could you run an entire server in a browser extension?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately there are small endaevours to run webservers inside of browser extensions.   Node.js makes a good fit because the binary is only ~6.5mb and can easily be included inside of an extension without concerns for bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The links below are people who have succesfully run node.js inside of the browser using different methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rawkes.com/articles/running-node.html&quot;&gt;Embedding and running node.js within a firefox xul extension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iceddev/node-chromify&quot;&gt;node-chromify&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/danielconnor/chrome-node&quot;&gt;chrome-node&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to see current attempts such as tent.io port their servers to node.js.   At this point, there is no reason why you couldn’t bundle the server inside an easy to install extension.   I would definitely then try out a distributed social network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look forward to hearing from those interested!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://thomasdav.is/the-problem-with-distributed-social-networks</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://thomasdav.is/the-problem-with-distributed-social-networks</guid>
        
        
        <category>distributed</category>
        
        <category>social</category>
        
        <category>networks</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The obligatory refutation of RPC (Meteor.js)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This is a very old blog post from my younger years&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have just been reading through all the discussion of Meteor.js on Hackernews and noticed that the discussion had very little critique.   So here are just a few articles to think about and at the very least this post hopes to facilitate some discussion of the cons of the Meteor.js approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;amp;q=cache:LylgA_fL8q4J:web.uvic.ca/~erikj/seng422/resources/rest_paper.pdf+&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;pid=bl&amp;amp;srcid=ADGEESjYHfPLfpUiFhk4xLz6u9tSLXyTtcs6RVvV9ZdSqcNFjPNZ6iKmU5N7Ij0kYphZXmEqAL0VvVYGE9kT14vn7SveDWswWyL71LXn2neko4XEiM5PKaV_ZP5pH2kksIpaPgtcTgmA&amp;amp;sig=AHIEtbSBz804J-e96OlGr7I-LyV4ZDiLBQ&amp;amp;pli=1&quot;&gt;REST：An Alternative to RPC for Web Services Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a front-end developer this publication articulates well some of my strongest concerns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2316005&quot;&gt;Now.js released on Hackernews - 400 days ago&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A user &lt;code&gt;jerf&lt;/code&gt; gives an indepth critique and should proove a valuable insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://armstrongonsoftware.blogspot.com.au/2008/05/road-we-didnt-go-down.html&quot;&gt;Erlang - This the road we didn’t go down&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More food for thought&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-thoughts&quot;&gt;My thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wrote this up in a matter of minutes so can’t do the duty of clarifying any refutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though my quick points would be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clients are now more tightly coupled to servers and actually influence the servers development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Versioning of data/API’s becomes more complex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security becomes more complex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should be striving towards improving our understanding of REST to tackle the problems or at least theorizing how RPC can solve them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nowjs.com/&quot;&gt;Now.js&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/substack/dnode&quot;&gt;dnode&lt;/a&gt; have been around for a while now.  They have already managed to grow a culture of negative sentiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully some experts chime in and give us the other side of the story&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://thomasdav.is/the-obligatory-refutation-of-rpc</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://thomasdav.is/the-obligatory-refutation-of-rpc</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is the Internet an extension of human memory?</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This is a very old blog post from my younger years&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just my rough thoughts on excessive computing and human memory.   Possibly analogous to “are calculators bad for teaching math”.   Would love to hear thoughts on the matter, sorry in advance for my poor articulation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-observation&quot;&gt;My observation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve noticed when I wish to recall facts/knowledge I without hesitation open a new tab and perform a quick search.   Most of the time I find what I was after instantly.   What I find humorous is that when I go to recall the information my brain tells me to search and what keywords to search for.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So effectively what I have done is when I first acquired the information I associated the “search” action with the memory instead of what I actually found.   Essentially creating a shortcut/middleman to a quality repository of information but possibly sacrificed through laziness my ability to actually absorb the information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using my memory normally I would generally look straight for the fact or information I was after.   This association of search terms is probably a symptom of laziness/convenience and I am unsure of whether it enhances or un-enhances my productivity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple/personal example would be when learning a programming language I sometimes don’t really bother learning the syntax or methods as I know I can simply search for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-dilemma&quot;&gt;My dilemma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this can be most convenient in some circumstances because I can quickly find huge repositories of quality information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though as a biological human having epiphanies is a fast way to let your conscious evolve.    But to have a basic epiphany I believe humans by accident/coincidence put together premises they have acquired over an arbitrary amount of time.   But due to me not really committing information directly to my memory I have less premises to call on when thinking.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that my ability to be creative is impaired because all I am turning my memory into is the “Contents Page” of what I know.   So instead of a novel, I am a dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A practical solution could be to make a much more conscious effort when consuming information to store the ideas behind it first then store the path to the full repository.   I presume this already happens quite a bit but realizing how many web sites I have visited makes me skeptical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I would love to hear what you have to say on the subject!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://thomasdav.is/is-the-internet-an-extension-of-human-memory</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://thomasdav.is/is-the-internet-an-extension-of-human-memory</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
